<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>Piero Mattos</title><description>I'm an iOS software engineer from Jundiaí, SP, Brazil.</description><link>https://pmattos.me</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 23:21:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 23:21:54 +0000</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://pmattos.me/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pmattos.me/posts/2020/3/8/c-is-a-very-nice-high-level-language</guid><title>"C is a very nice high-level language"</title><description></description><link>https://pmattos.me/posts/2020/3/8/c-is-a-very-nice-high-level-language</link><pubDate>Sun, 8 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>"C is a very nice high-level language"</h1><p>Yesterday I stumbled upon this 1982 video from the AT&amp;T Archives about the then new UNIX operating system. Five minutes in, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Kernighan">Brian Kernighan</a> provides an overview of how the UNIX operating system worked and how one could write a simple program for it using a novel feature the system had: the ability to pipe an output from one program as the input to another. Amazing video. It gives us a really good sense of what computing and programming was like back then and is full of interesting tidbits and quotes like the one in the title of this post.</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tc4ROCJYbm0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pmattos.me/posts/2020/1/18/my-experience-at-nsbrazil-2019</guid><title>My experience at NSBrazil 2019</title><description></description><link>https://pmattos.me/posts/2020/1/18/my-experience-at-nsbrazil-2019</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>My experience at NSBrazil 2019</h1><p>Recently, I had the chance to attend <a href="https://nsbrazil.com/en/">NSBrazil 2019</a>, the biggest iOS developer conference in Brazil. The conference took place on the first weekend of November 2019 in São Paulo, and was full of interesting talks about iOS development and Swift.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20200118-nsbrazil-2019.jpg"/><p>I know it’s been a while already, but since the conference talk videos were just recently published on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/cocoaheadsbr">CocoaHeads Brasil YouTube channel</a>, I though I’d list my favorite talks and maybe you can learn something new while watching them, just as I did. I hope you enjoy it!</p><p><em>Quick disclaimer: except for one of them, all of the talks are in Brazilian Portuguese.</em></p><h2>Daniel Steinberg - A feel for Combine</h2><p>Daniel is an amazing public speaker and a long-time conference speaker. A few months back I watched his talk about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2eK8voQeokk">The Swift Behind SwiftUI at Hacking With Swift Live 2019</a> and it’s one of the most educational and entertaining talks I’ve seen so far.</p><p>At NSBrazil, Daniel talked about Combine, Apple’s new framework, which works in conjunction with SwiftUI to provide the new declarative syntax to create user interfaces for all of Apple’s platforms. Definitely worth a watch:</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3vz1grUFve8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><h2>Txai Wieser - Quem botou Swift na minha UI?</h2><p>Txai gave us a little bit of insight into how SwiftUI works behind the scenes, explaining how views are laid out and how the relationships they have with their parent or child views affects their layout.</p><p>Amazing talk, as it gives you a more instinctive feel for how SwiftUI works and can greatly facilitate the transition from working with UIKit to SwiftUI, which we’ll all inevitably have to go through sooner or later.</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XkKRstZs5bY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><h2>Bruno Rocha - Creating iOS apps with Buck without working in the Valley</h2><p>Bruno’s talk was about how he and the iOS teams at iFood changed the way they work with their Xcode projects by using Buck, a build tool created by Facebook that can facilitate working with big codebases by providing better modularity, dependency management and incremental builds. Great talk!</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0HI0psqVdws" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><h2>Igor Ferreira - Localização e Internacionalização: adaptando o seu app para onde a zoeira tem limite</h2><p>Igor’s talk was certainly the most enthusiastic one of the whole conference. By sharing a little of his experience working with Localization and Internationalization of apps with us, he was able to bring to light a lot of common misconceptions and mistakes developers encounter when doing this type of work. Very useful content.</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/H_9cUm99A5I" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pmattos.me/posts/2019/8/18/cracking-the-code-of-cicada-3301</guid><title>“Cracking the Code of Cicada 3301”</title><description></description><link>https://pmattos.me/posts/2019/8/18/cracking-the-code-of-cicada-3301</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>“Cracking the Code of Cicada 3301”</h1><p>What a fascinating short documentary about Cicada 3301 and the puzzles it has created. Definitely worth watching.</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RatbYqc0-jE" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe><p>The video above is only part 1 of the documentary, check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCajXeitgFL-rb5-gXI-aG8Q">Great Big Story YouTube channel</a> to find the other parts.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pmattos.me/posts/2019/7/11/my-experience-at-apples-2019-wwdc</guid><title>My experience at Apple’s 2019 WWDC</title><description></description><link>https://pmattos.me/posts/2019/7/11/my-experience-at-apples-2019-wwdc</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>My experience at Apple’s 2019 WWDC</h1><h2>“This was a WWDC for the ages”</h2><p>That’s how Marco Arment described it during one of the latest episodes of his Under The Radar show, a podcast about independent iOS app development. Marco is an independent software developer, responsible for the popular iOS podcasts app Overcast and one of the most active voices in the iOS developers and Apple fans communities.</p><p>Some might see Marco’s assessment of Apple’s Worldwide Developers Conference as exaggerated. After all, this was the event Apple unveiled a thousand-dollar monitor stand at, how could it have been that great, right?</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-pro-display-xdr-stand.jpg"/><p>Besides the obviously overpriced monitor stand which ended up highjacking a lot of the headlines after the event, Apple did introduce a pletora of new and interesting things aimed at the event's main audience - developers. New and updated APIs for all its platforms, new user-facing features such as Dark Mode on iOS, Sign In with Apple, the formal split of iPadOS into its own (even more) tailored version of iOS, iPad apps for Mac, SwiftUI, just to count a few.</p><p>This was the most packed WWDC of the last few years and all of these announcements left developers with a lot of work on their hands to do before the new versions of Apple operating systems ship in the Fall, if they want their apps to be up to par with user's expectations. This was one of the main justifications for Marco's assessment of the conference.</p><p>I agree with him. Not only because of everything that was announced by Apple on this event, but also because this was my first time attending it, which was a dream come true for a long time Apple fan. So, at least to me, this was indeed a WWDC for the ages.</p><p>Here’s a little about what my experience was like and what I consider to be the most valuable thing I got from the event.</p><h2>Registration and keynote anticipation</h2><p>Sunday morning is when registration for attendees begins. This means developers who are attending the event can go to the San Jose McEnery Convention Center and pick up their event badges, as well as the souvenirs Apple has prepared for them. As was the case for past years, this year the company provided developers with a custom made WWDC 19 jacket, and a selection of magnetic pins, which included some Apple- themed ones such as the Memoji version of Tim Cook, or an Apple logo, as well as one with the flag for developer's home countries.</p><p>After registering for the event I spent some time around the convention center getting to know my fellow developers. After that, I visited Apple Park’s Visitors Center, and went to Apple’s “old“ HQ on Infinite Loop. This was a good opportunity to buy some Apple branded souvenir which is exclusively sold at the two stores located at Apple’s main corporates campuses.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-convention-center.jpg"/><h2>Keynote day</h2><p>Monday morning is when the event kicks off for everyone and, since I wanted to grab a good spot to watch the keynote, I arrived at the convention center early in the morning, at around 5AM. To my surprise there were already about a thousand people in front of me in line, but I was lucky to be at the right place in line when the staff split it up into separate portions to enter the hall, and I ended up getting a front row spot to the left of the stage, which was awesome.</p><p>The keynote itself wasn't that long, as Apple tries to keep it under two and a half hours in length, but it was really fast-paced, as they needed to show a lot in that relatively small amount of time. The biggest moment for me was when unveiled the new Mac Pro, not because I'm interested in buying one anytime soon, but rather because this has been anticipated and talked about so much over the last few years on one of the other podcasts I listen to, the Accidental Tech Podcast. I feel like this was a moment all of us listeners of this podcast were sharing with the same level of excitement because we had been passively taking part in all the conversation around this product for so long, and seeing it finally come to light was awesome!</p><p>In the afternoon of the first conference day, Apple holds what is called the State of the Union for its platforms, this is when presenters go into more technical details about what was introduced during the keynote, as well as some things that weren’t talked about in the morning.</p><h2>Mac Pro and Pro Display XDR</h2><p>Apple set up a separate venue for showing off the new Mac Pro and its capabilities across the street from the Convention Center. Only the media and special guests were allowed in on Monday, but during the entire day on Tuesday developers could sign up for a time slot to be able to check out the products in person, so I did.</p><p>It was really cool to be able to enter one of these product demo rooms that Apple usually sets up for displaying new products, which is something we only usually see on YouTube videos. The new Mac Pro looks great in person, and the new Pro Display XDR is absolutely stunning.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-mac-pro.jpg"/><h2>Sessions, Labs and Staff</h2><p>During the rest of the week, multiple sessions about the new technologies introduced take place inside of the McEnery Convention Center. Labs are also set up where developers can talk directly to Apple engineers to ask for help with their apps regarding the existing or newly released APIs, or just hang around and meet new people.</p><p>Apple employees are always really nice and helpful both at the labs and outside them! Special thanks to all the Apple Store staff who help organize the event and keep the energy level really high during the entire week!</p><h2>Satellite events</h2><p>Over the years, it has become tradition for many other events to take place during the week of WWDC. This includes conferences such as AltConf (where an Apple-themed escape room was set up) and Layers, and also special events such as the live recordings of popular Apple- related podcasts, such as the aforementioned ATP, Connected, Swift over Coffee, and The Talk Show.</p><p>I did manage to attend the live shows for both ATP and The Talk Show. The first one was really funny, as the three hosts - Casey Liss, Marco Arment, and John Siracusa - dissected the much anticipated announcement of the new Mac Pro, and the latter one was ones of the highlights of the week, as John Gruber masterfully interviewed Apple's Craig Federighi (SVP of Software Engineering) and Greg Joswiak (VP of iOS, iPad and iPhone Product Marketing), a conversation filled with great insights about how the latest set of announcements and products come to be and what they mean for the future of software development on Apple’s platforms.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-atp-live.jpg"/><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-daring-fireball.jpg"/><p>As I work for IBM, I was also invited to a dinner on Wednesday night to celebrate the partnership between Apple and IBM. This took place at Caffé Macs Alves, near Apple’s Infinite Loop campus, and a lot of Apple and IBM employees were there. It was a great opportunity to meet people from both companies with whom I work with from a distance, or who are developing the technologies we use to create our apps. It was a very pleasant evening with some very nice people.</p><p>On Thursday night, the traditional Bash, an outdoor concert which is part of the conference agenda, took place in Discovery Meadow, a couple of blocks away from the convention center. This year the band invited to perform was Weezer. The Bash itself is very cool, Apple sets up a lot of fun games for people to play, and serves drinks and food.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-bash.jpg"/><h2>Is attending WWDC worth it?</h2><p>A lot of people make the case that attending WWDC is not worth it, nowadays Apple live streams both the keynote and all of the sessions that happen during the week, and watching these at home can arguably be better than watching them in person.</p><p>With this being my first time attending the event, I didn’t really know what to expect. But one thing is clear to me already, the last thing you go to WWDC for is the keynote and sessions. There is so much more happening in and around the event that matter so much more than these presentations. Of course, watching Apple executives and employees present what’s new in person is really cool, but the real value of the conference lies in the other activities you take part in during the week.</p><p>Be it attending one of the Labs to discuss the latest APIs with the people responsible for them, meeting new people who have the same interests as you, grabbing lunch or a beer with someone you just connected with, attending a podcast live show, going to one of the other parallel conferences, or simply just talking to someone about what was announced while in line to use the restroom, there’s never a dull moment.</p><p>WWDC is about so much more than new versions of operating systems and APIs, the most valuable thing I got from attending the event were the friends I made while there and the immense boost of inspiration I got from these new connections.</p><p>So yes, it was undoubtedly worth it to me. Maybe I’ll change my mind after attending for a second or third time, but I have a feeling this is something all WWDCs are able to provide, regardless of what is announced on stage.</p><img src="https://pmattos.me/images/20190711-rusty-bridge-view.jpg"/><h2>Special thanks</h2><p>I wanted to say thanks to some of the people that helped make my experience at WWDC even more awesome than I expected it would be.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/lukabratos">Luka Bratos</a>, for keeping me great company while in line for the keynote.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/BrianCYoung">Brian Young</a>, for the awesome time during the keynote and for the great stories shared.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aiden-olfert-b97b10186">Aiden Olfert</a>, congratulations on your achievements at such a young age.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/CraigTashman">Craig Tashman</a>, for sharing lunch with me and for showing me your company’s awesome app <a href="https://twitter.com/LiquidTextCorp">LiquidText</a>.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ymkim0design">Yongmin Kim</a>, for also sharing lunch with me and for being so nice, I hope you have a great time in Canada!</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/danielsxu">Daniel Xu</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/geoffclifton">Geoff Clifton</a>, for the awesome time and the ride back on Wednesday night.</p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/ChrisAljoudi">Chris Aljoudi</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/camdeardorff">Cameron Deardorff</a>, for the great conversations, shared beers, laughs, and for all the help when I needed it.</p><p>I hope we can meet again next year! See you in San Jose!</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>